<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> 
<rss version="2.0"> 
    <channel> 
        <title>monotone - distributed version control</title> 
        <link>http://monotone.ca/releases.xml</link> 
        <description>monotone releases with links to the sources.</description> 
        <language>en</language> 
        <pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2007 22:35:33 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <item> 
            <title>monotone 0.37 released</title> 
            <description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
Time for a new, and currently not so regular release.  This is
version 0.37, with quite a number of changes that I imagine would be
interesting for quite a lot of people.
</p>

<h2>Changes</h2>

<ul>
<li>mtn db kill_rev_locally now checks for an existing workspace
before the revision is killed and tries to apply the changes
of this particular revision back to the workspace to allow
easy re-committing afterwards

<li>the "--brief" switch for mtn annotate has been renamed to
"--revs-only" for clarity

<li>mtn help now lists the commands (and their aliases) available
within a group, so its easier to get an overview which commands
are available at all

<li>the "MTN_MERGE=diffutils" merger (provided by std_hooks.lua)
was improved. It now accepts a MTN_MERGE_DIFFUTILS environment
variable which can be used to control its behaviour
through comma-separated "key[=value]" entries. Currently
supported entries are "partial" for doing a partial
batch/non-modal 3-way merge conflict "resolution" which uses
embedded content conflict markers and "diff3opts=[...]" and
"sdiffopts=[...]" for passing arbitrary options to the used
"diff3" and "sdiff" tools. When used in combination with "mtn
merge_into_workspace" this way one especially can achieve a
CVS/SVN style non-modal workspace-based merging.

<li>There is a new revision selector: "p:REV" selects the
parent(s) of revision REV.  For example, if a revision has
one parent,

    <code>mtn diff -r p:REV -r REV</code>

will show the changes made in that revision.

<li>Monotone now uses the Perl-Compatible Regular Expression
(PCRE) library for all regular expressions, instead of the
boost::regex library.  This means that external Boost
libraries are no longer required to build or use Monotone.
If building from source, you will still need the Boost headers
available somewhere.  See INSTALL for details.

<li>PCRE's syntax for regular expressions is a superset of
boost::regex's syntax; it is unlikely that any existing
.mtn-ignore files or other user uses of regexps will break.
The manual now contains detailed documentation of the regexp
syntax, borrowed from PCRE itself.

<li>the format of "mtn automate inventory" has changed to basic_io.
This fixes a couple of corner cases where the old format
returned wrong information and introduces new capabilities like
restricted output, recognized attribute changes, and more.
For a complete overview on the new format, please take a look
in the appropriate manual section.
</ul>

<h2>Bugs fixed</h2>

<ul>
<li>mtn automate heads called without a branch argument now properly
returns the head revisions of the workspace's branch if called
over mtn automate stdio

<li>mtn commit no longer crashes if it creates a revision whose
roster already exists, i.e. was left behind by the command
`mtn db kill_rev_locally REV` (savannah #18990)
</ul>

<h2>Documentation changes</h2>

<ul>
<li>the documentation of the "--revs-only" (formerly "--brief")
switch for the annotate command didn't match its actual
behavior, this has been fixed

<li>documentation for the "ssh_agent_add" command was missing
and has been added
</ul>

<h2>Other</h2>

<ul>
<li>contrib/usher.cc has been removed. Please use the
net.venge.monotone.contrib.usher branch instead.
</ul>

<h2>Internal</h2>

<ul>
<li>Update SQLite to 3.4.1.

<li>Update Lua to 5.1.2 plus latest bug fixes.

<li>Update Botan to 1.5.10.

<li>Internal use of regular expressions has been almost eliminated.
(Regular expressions are still used for .mtn-ignore and the
--show-encloser feature of mtn diff, and are still available to
Lua hooks.)
</ul>

]]>
            </description>
            <pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2007 22:35:33 +0000</pubDate>
            <enclosure url="http://monotone.ca/downloads/0.37/monotone-0.37.tar.gz" length="5259352" type="application/octet-stream"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss> 
